<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A small treatise concerning evil thoughts and imaginations and concerning good thoughts and heavenly meditations ... / by W. S.</title>
            <author>Shewen, William, 1631?-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59954</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3423</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33809</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13567415</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13567415</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100326</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59954)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100326)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1049:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A small treatise concerning evil thoughts and imaginations and concerning good thoughts and heavenly meditations ... / by W. S.</title>
                  <author>Shewen, William, 1631?-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Spiritual life.</term>
               <term>Theology, Practical.</term>
               <term>Good and evil.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100326:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Small TREATISE Concerning <hi>Evil Thoughts and Imaginations,</hi> And concerning <hi>Good Thoughts and Heavenly MEDITATIONS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>SHEWING, How every true Chriſtian muſt know the one conſumed by the brightneſs of the appearance of Chriſt; and the other ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected and brought into the Obedience of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>ALSO, A few words concerning the Life, State, and enjoyment of a true Chriſtian, and of the true Chriſtian Worſhip, what it ſtands in, and how performed.</p>
            <q>Then the Lord God took the man and put him into the Garden of Eden, to dreſs it and to keep it,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Gen. 1.27, 28.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>W. S.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1679.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:100326:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100326:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>MY chief end and aim in this ſmall Treatiſe concerning Thoughts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is, that thou mayeſt be informed how to attain unto that Primitive
<note n="*" place="margin">As thou comeſt into the Image of God again, thou wilt ſubdue the earthly image, have do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over thy own thoughts, government over thy will deſire, and affections: This is the Primitive power Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind was endued withal; for the nature of the whole Creation is in Man; and he that hath perfect dominion or rule over himſelf, all things elſe are under his feet; where this is want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſorder and confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on abounds, being ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to that Spirit that leads even nature it ſelf out of courſe. Gen. 1.27, 28.</note> Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Power, and Dominion, which Mankind had, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Tranſgreſſion entred the World; wherein he did, and could ſubdue the Earth, have Dominion over it, and over all the Creatures God had made, moving upon
<pb facs="tcp:100326:3"/>the face of the Earth, in the Air and Water alſo; and and give them all Names according to their Nature, and to dreſs and keep the Garden ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Command of God: for God never commanded any thing (as Man's Duty) that was impoſſible; he had Wiſdom and Power given to him to obſerve and obey whatſoever was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned him; the Serpent could not force or compel, though he could entice and allure; yet till he was yielded to, till conſent through deceiveableneſs of the Bait, begot a vain hope to better his estate, till he gave way to fooliſh Thoughts and Conſultations, he kept his Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, Place, and Habitation in Paradice: But when he entered into the Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he went forward into a multitude of Thoughts and Inventions, till he was driven to the greateſt diſtance from God; in which ſtate he doth and will remain, till he come to embrace the hand that ſmites him, and obey that
<pb facs="tcp:100326:3"/>voice that calls unto him in the cool of the day,
<note place="margin">To believe and obey the Spirit of God which he hath ſent into the world, placed in mens hearts, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinceth and repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth for Sin, is the only way &amp; means which God hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration, life, and ſalvation of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and is indeed the Chriſt of God, which in Scripture hath many names, but is but one pure eternal holy thing.</note> and to learn of that Spirit that reproveth him, and convinceth him of Sin, and maketh him afraid to ſee the face of God, becauſe he hath Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed his Law, and broken his Holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments: and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til he comes to believe, that he that wounds muſt heal, he that calls to account for evil do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, muſt ſave from it, and that the Reproofs of Inſtruction is the way to life, and that to be ſlain with the Flaming Sword that turns every way to guard the Tree of Life, is the way to live again: And that through the Spirit of Judgment and burning, Redemption, Salvation, Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and Everlasting Felicity is again to be come unto<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the Spirit of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Obedience that took Life by obeying the
<pb facs="tcp:100326:4"/>Serpent, muſt come to Death, muſt be Mortified, Slain and Buried out of ſight alſo, in all his Thoughts, Imaginations, Inventions, Willing, Running, Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending; in all his Wiſdom, Knowledge, Prudence, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding alſo: theſe muſt all be ſtopped, bowed under, and confounded, or brought to nought, before he can enter into rest again, or know what the Sabbath of the Lord is, which the outward Sabbath was a ſign of.</p>
            <p>Mankind is never ſafe while he is his own keeper, while he is willing, running, and working for himſelf; while he is guided and led by his own Will, Mind, Knowledge, Wiſdom, Prudence, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding; he is never at quiet, never content and ſatisfied, never at reſt, being gone from the Fountain of Living Water, though he labours and toils to hew out Ciſterns that he thinks may ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply his want; yet they prove ſo broken, that they will hold no water, no refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for his Soul, no ſatisfaction nor content for his mind, though he toil and
<pb facs="tcp:100326:4"/>dig in the earth, and ſearch the dark corners thereof: And though in his thoughts and imaginations he aſcends up into Heaven, and makes his Neſts among the Stars, his labour is all vain and fruitleſs, when the day of ſhaking comes, when the melting of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments come, all proves but as a bed too ſhort, and as a covering too narrow, and as one that walks by the light of his own ſparks, and warms himſelf by the fire of his own kindling, but in the end lies down in ſorrow. All theſe things thou who art a Child of Light, and of the day, underſtandeſt right well; therefore art thou made willing in the day of God's power to die to thy ſelf dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to give up and reſign thy ſelf to the daily Croſs,
<note n="*" place="margin">While men live in the fleſh, they cannot pleaſe God; but its poſſible to be dead thereto and live in the Spirit on this ſide the Grave</note> till thou doſt become dead, cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, and buried alſo; till which, thou cannot avoid thinking thy own thoughts, ſpeaking thy own words, and doing thy own works, and following thy own
<pb facs="tcp:100326:5"/>will, thoughts, and inventions, from which ſprang thy miſery, and in which it continues, ſo long as thou art alive in thy ſelf, and at home in the body, thou art really dead and abſent from the Lord.</p>
            <p>For it is only thoſe that are dead and ſuffer with Chriſt that come to know a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and reigning with him, over all worldly Rudiments, over all carnal Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, over all filthineſs of Fleſh and Spirit, over all Principalities and Powers, and Spiritual Wickedneſſes in high places; over all Thoughts and Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, over all Deſire, Will and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; theſe are they that ariſe and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend with him up unto the Father, and that ſits down in heavenly places with him, at the right hand of God, and that have converſe in Heaven, talks with God as a man talks with his Friend, he holds his Face with Joy and great De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light. As thou comeſt hither, thou art come into the Reſtauration indeed, thou haſt found that which was loſt indeed; thou art come from the Eaſt, West,
<pb facs="tcp:100326:5"/>North, and South, and ſate down in the Kingdom with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> indeed, and art ceaſed from thy own works as God did from his, and art entred into the bleſſed reſt that God hath prepared; <hi>all which is poſſible to him that believes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore let none put the good and evil day afar off, for the Kingdom of Heaven is at hand, and many are li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving witneſſes of the coming of it, and do enjoy Righteouſneſs, Peace, and Joy in the Holy Ghoſt, in which the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſtands. And God is Omnipreſent, and thoſe that enjoy the Light of his Countenance, dwell in Heaven, and are within the Gates thereof; which though they stand open, no unclean thing can enter.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:100326:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100326:6"/>
            <head>A Small TREATISE Concerning Thoughts and Imaginations.</head>
            <p>EVil Thoughts and Imaginations, are great troublers of the World of Mankind; and it is a great plague and miſery which man is accompanied and ſurrounded with, who is given up to follow and obey his own evil Thoughts and Imaginations; or to walk ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to them: It was a fore judgment pronounced againſt the diſobedient rebellious Jews, in the Word of the Lord by <hi>Jeremy,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Hear O earth, behold I will bring evil upon this people, even the fruit of their thoughts.</hi> And the Lord by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith, <hi>I have ſtretched out my hand all day to a rebellious people which walked in a way that was not good, after their own thoughts, which are thoughts of iniquity, and the act of violence
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100326:7"/>is in their hands.</hi> Alſo 'tis written, <hi>Every thought and imagination of mans heart are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly evil, and that continually.</hi> And very great is the miſery, bondage, and ſlavery of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind in this eſtate; he is an enemy to God, and to himſelf, and to his Neighbour and Brother, <hi>Waſting and deſtruction are in their paths, who have not God in all their thoughts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now reader, that which is principally on my mind, is, to ſet before thee a certain in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible way, how thou mayeſt come to be ſaved from following or obeying thy own thoughts, and to gain ſtrength againſt, and get victory over all thy imaginations that are evil; and alſo how thou mayeſt attain to good thoughts, and heavenly Meditations in the room thereof; and how thou mayeſt come to know every good thought, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, brought into the obedience of Chriſt, and every evil thought and imagination de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, and conſumed with the breath of his mouth, and the brightneſs of his appearing. And when thou art re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored and brought into the ſame eſtate mankind was in before tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<note place="margin">Evil thoughts muſt be conſumed, and good thoughts muſt be ſubject and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to Chriſt.</note> even into the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of God, how thou muſt then dreſs and keep the Garden. Thou muſt then watch over, and in the Wiſdom
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100326:7"/>and Power of God, govern thy thoughts, leſt the Serpent beguile thee as he did <hi>Eve.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Thou muſt underſtand that
<note n="*" place="margin">Many in their carnal thoughts and imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations conceive and affirm that it was the outward Earth God curſed, and that it would have brought forth no bryars, thorns, nor thiſtles (which are good Creatures in their places) if man had not ſinned, ſuch thoughts are vain and fooliſh; for all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God are good, the Fire and Air, Earth and Water, Sun, Moon, and Stars, and all the product of them, and they all ſtand and remain in the bleſſing, and keep their place, ſtate, and order ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the will of God, and are obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent unto him, and he is the upholder thereof by the word of his power.</note> the ground evil thoughts and imaginations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe from, is now that which God in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning curſed: from this ground ſpring all the Bryars, Thorns, and Thiſtles, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hurtful Weeds in the world of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, in whoſe heart they began to ſpring, grow, and increaſe, even ſo ſoon as he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to loſe his Faith in God his Maker, &amp; incline to hearken to the voice of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and give credit to his lyes, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got a vain thought; from whence a falſe hope ſprung, that they ſhould by eating the forbidden fruit better their conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100326:8"/>
               <hi>be as Gods,</hi> according as the Serpent told the Woman (the weaker Veſſel) and by this falſe hope, grounded upon the thoughts and imaginations, entered the firſt tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; then when the temptation was entred into, and ſin committed thoughts and ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations began to multiply and fill the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient earthly heart of mankind; who having now turned his back upon the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly, ſlighten the voice and command of God, who was his <hi>Teacher</hi> and <hi>Lawgiver,</hi> and
<note n="*" place="margin">How man loſt his ſtate at firſt. Let thoſe that are reſtored thereto a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, take warning thereby, for the ſame temptation &amp; danger attends.</note> lent his ear to the wicked one, and gave up his mind and heart to obey him, even with thoughts it was all for the beſt. Thus poor mankind being deceived with vain thoughts, and falſe hope, loſt his habitation and dwelling-place in Paradice; which after he had tranſgreſs'd, he ſtill thought to keep; for he was ſoon convinced he had done amiſs in cating the forbidden Fruit; and fear poſſeſt his heart, when he heard the voice of God in the cool of the day, and therefore ſought means to cover and hide himſelf from the ſight of God: but herein his thoughts were vain, and his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to no purpoſe; the Woman, Man, and Serpent, all received the fruits of their
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100326:8"/>own doings; nothing but life, good and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing were known before; now death evil, and curſing the fruit and effect of diſobedience, (which as I have ſaid, entred firſt by giving place to a vain thought and deſire in
<note n="*" place="margin">Wicked men and ſinners of theſe times and ages of the world, propoſe not that end to themſelves, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil needs not lay ſuch baits &amp; ſnares to win them to his obedience, being ſuch vaſſals to him, that his motions and commands are ſufficient.</note> hope to gain and better their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate) become the daily companions of mankind, who found, and finds by woful experience, that ſaying true, <hi>When ſin is fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed it brings forth death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So man having loſt his place in the Garden which God planted, through neglecting his work which God appointed him to do, which was <hi>to dreſs it, and to keep it;</hi> for the Garden needed dreſſing and keeping before the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden Fruit was eaten, before Innocency was loſt, before ſin was committed, hefore the Serpent became a Tempter, Devil, and Deſtroyer.</p>
            <p>And this ariſeth in my mind to teſlifie to all the wiſe in heart, that after they are come to find that which was loſt, to witneſs a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoration, and Regeneration, and a returning into <hi>Eden</hi> again, into Innocency again, they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100326:9"/>have work there to do, <hi>Dreſſing</hi> and <hi>Keeping</hi> are two very ſignificant words: this was the buſineſs of mankind in the beginning, in the ſtate of Innocency; if he had not neglected this work, ſlighted the Light, Power, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and Glory of God, with which he was repleniſhed, he had never fell; when the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation got into a thought, if he had watched in the Light and Wiſdom of God, he would have ſeen and diſcovered the tendency of it, and have prevented its coming to a deſire and act: But firſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<note n="*" place="margin">The beginning, increaſe, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of ſin, and how to ſtop and prevent it.</note> place to a ſelfiſh thought, it ſoon ſprang to a hunger or deſire, thence into act, (this is the beginning and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of ſin at this day) which mankind in Innocency had, and hath power and wiſdom from God to prevent, if he abide in it, and keep in his watch-tower, the light and ſtrength of God, which is as near him as the temptation can be, and ſufficient to preſerve him: and where this work is neglected, men, yea, holy men fall, and ſin after the ſimilitude of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Trangreſſion, and are beguiled as the Serpent did <hi>Eve,</hi> drawn out of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, and a ſinleſs eſtate after they have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained unto it; therefore let none be high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded, but fear, and take the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:100326:9"/>for example, who when he was tempted, did not hunger or deſire after the things preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, though very ſpacious in appearance, and accompanied with very large promiſes; even as the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> had: but 'tis written, while the temptation laſted he eat nothing; he let nothing in, gave no place to ſelfiſh thoughts, and enticements of the enemy: ſo when the temptation was over, Angels miniſtred unto him: Let this be the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of all the Children of Light, and as they do thereafter, the powerful ſalvation of God ſhall ſurround them <hi>and neither heights nor depths, Angels, Principalities, nor Powers, things preſen, or things to come, ſhall be able to ſeparate them from the love of God in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> This is as a word by the way.</p>
            <p>Now evil thoughts and
<note n="*" place="margin">They are as the wings of the great red Dragon, who troubles Heaven &amp; Earth, Angels and Men.</note> imaginations are of a multiplying nature, and do mainly increaſe and take root in the generali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of mankind; who, through evil works are eſtranged from the life of God, remaining a degenerate plant, ſprang from the ſeed of the evil doer, and dwells and labours in that ground which God hath curſed, and knows not the ſeed of the Woman to bruiſe the Serpents head, and to redeem and preſerve
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100326:10"/>him from following and obeying his own thoughts and imaginations, which are evil, and that continually. And indeed in that ſtate can be no otherwiſe, whether they lead into ſelf-ſinning, or ſelf-righteouſneſs, both are an abomination to the Lord, and deſtructive to the well-being of mankind, both temporal and eternal: for all the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs that hath been brought forth and acted in the world ſince the beginning, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan or appeared firſt in the thought; and the thought being cheriſhed and joyned to by the mind, will, and underſtanding, it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, and increaſeth into words and actions. That which is clean cannot proceed from that which is unclean; the heart of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind in the fall is univerſally corrupted, and deſperate wicked; and, as hath been ſaid, the thoughts and imaginations thereof are evil, and that continually: And before it can be otherwiſe, there is an abſolute neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity that every particular man and woman muſt know and experience: for, and in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, their hearts cleanſed, purged, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, and created anew, the ground muſt be made good, before the ſeed, the heavenly plant can grow, increaſe, and flouriſh there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; before good thoughts, heavenly thoughts, and meditations can ariſe, ſpring, and remain therein. And when this eſtate is known,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100326:10"/>witneſſed; and enjoyed, then to abide with him, dwell and walk with him, who hath wrought theſe mighty things in thee, and for thee, and in his wiſdom and power to dreſs and keep the Garden, the <hi>Heart,</hi> with all diligence, that that which would defile enter not again, creep in again, as it did in the beginning (which is poſſible.) Therefore what the Spirit of God put man upon in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning when he was a noble plant in <hi>Eden,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Man was to dreſs and keep the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den before Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion entred; and when he comes to know ſin and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion finiſhed, or reſtoration in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Innocency again, he muſt be exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the ſame work.</note> wholly a right Seed, <hi>viz.</hi> to dreſs and keep the Garden, ſo the Spirit of God now in this age ſaith to the Diſciples thereof; <hi>Watch and pray, leſt ye enter into temptation; (take heed) leſt as the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent beguiled</hi> Eve <hi>through his ſubtilty, ſo your minds ſhould be corrupted from the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plieity that is in Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this I teſtifie from certain know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that God hath ordained means where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by mankind, whoſe heart is ſo corrupted, that nothing that is good proceeds out of it, neither any thing that is heavenly, and of God ſprings up in it, that can live a moment, being ſo foul and ſo dark, (even like a foul
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100326:11"/>dark piece of earth outwardly, on which the Sun never ſhines, nor the rain falls) that man in this miſerable ſtate may come to know and experienye his foul heart cleanſed, purged, and ſanctified, as the Chriſtians in the Primitive times did;
<note place="margin">Though mankind may be in a ſtate like unto dry bones ſcattered in a Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, without mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and life, yet ſuch may come to unit eagain, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news and fleſh to come upon them, and to receive the breath of life, and to know God alſo, whoſe work it is; who works mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous things in the Earth, and in the Heavens; as thoſe who go down into the deeps be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold.</note> 
               <hi>Such were ſome of you, but now are you waſhed, clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and ſanctified,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>the fallow ground may be plowed up, and bear ſeed, and the wilderneſs may become a fruitful field, and ſtreams may break forth in the deſare, and the deſart may come to rejoyce, and to bloſsom as a Roſe; crooked things may be made ſtreight, and rough places ſmooth; great heavy dark high Mountains may be brought down and removed; yea, (melted at the preſence of God) and the low valleys may be ezalted; yea the wilderneſs may become like</hi> Eden, <hi>and the deſart like the garden of the Lord.</hi> All theſe mighty works and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders hath the Lord wrought in this age, in and for a remnant, who are come to the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of the Propheſies, are living wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100326:11"/>of the ſame, and do in his Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and Power, proclaim that the love and mercy of God towards loſt man is univerſal, and that his hand is ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
<note n="*" place="margin">Fallen man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not help himſelf, therefore the eye of God pittieth him, and his hand is ſtretched out to help him: he is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly required to lay hold and depend upon the ſame, and it will bring falvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to his houſe.</note> forth to help him out of the ſnare, pit, and deep dark dungeon, wherein he is fallen; out of which he cannot by all his ſtrength, wiſdom, and invention help himſelf; and ſo ſet him at liberty, that he may run the ways of his Commandments with delight, and that he may come again to ſtand upright, as God made man in the beginning; and lay aſide all his thoughts and inventions wherein he cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted himſelf; and to bring him into ſuch a ſtate and condition, that he may be able to do all things that are good, to think good thoughts, ſpeak good words, and do good works; and to eſchew and avoid the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary: this to know and be able to do, is the <hi>one thing</hi> needful, wihtout which all men are miſerable, let their knowledge, wildom, and profeſſion of Religion, Opinion, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention be what it will.</p>
            <p>Therefore my mind is in good will to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, having received knowledge and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100326:12"/>of the means God hath ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the good and ſalvation of mankind: And being ſomething acquainted with the two great myſteries of Godlineſs &amp; Iniquity, and the way and working of each, to impart and ſignifie ſomething of the ſame in a few words, to inſtruct and inform thoſe to whom this my teſtimony may come, how they may attain thereunto, and how they may come to be rid of thoſe troubleſome companions, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Evil Thoughts and Imaginations that do, may, or ſhall ariſe in their hearts, whila corrupted; and how the ſame may be puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and made a holy habitation for God, as it was before ſin entred, before Innocency was loſt, before the Serpent deceived the weaker veſſel, when all was good, yea very good.</p>
            <p>The way that leadeth thereto, I affirm and declare to be as followeth; and whoever thou art that haſt a mind or deſire to find that which is loſt, obſerve, believe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive what I ſay or write, as <hi>Truth;</hi> not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived or learned by Tradition, but by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimental powerful work and operation of the Spirit of Truth in my own Heart, Mind, and Conſcience: and what I have ſaid, or ſhall ſay, is, and ſhall be according to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures, and witneſſed to by them; for I cannot write contrary to them, being in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100326:12"/>unity with them, &amp; with the juſt mens ſpirits that wrote them. Firſt then know thou, O man, whoever thou art, and whatever thy thoughts and imaginations are, how far ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thou art run into corruption, darkneſs, and degeneration from the ſtate of innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, purity, and holineſs; yet there is a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Divine Light attends thee, though thou art darkneſs it-ſhines in thee, in order to ſhow thee thy way out of it; though thou art degenerated and run from God into the earth, yet this pure light &amp; Spirit of God follows thee, and calls thee back again; and thou mayſt in this ſtate hear it as a voice be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind thee, ſaying, <hi>Return, return, this is the way, come and walk in it;</hi> this is the kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and love of God to thee in his Son, who is the light of the world, and lighteth every one that cometh therein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to;
<note place="margin">If men would hear and obey the voice of the Son of God, Death, Hell nor the Grave could not hinder them from Salvation.</note> if thou hear and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey this voice of the light of the Son of God, though thou wert dead in ſin, and buried as in a grave, thou ſhalt ariſe and come forth, and live before him; the bars and gates of Hell ſhall not be able to retain thee: But if thou ſlight and deſpiſe the Light of God that vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits thee, and ſhut'ſt thy ear againſt its voice, it will be as a thouſand witneſſes againſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100326:13"/>thee, while thou rebelleſt againſt it, and art found following thy own thoughts and ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, and doing the thing that is evil; for this Light I ſpeak of, is the eye of the Lord, that runs too and fro through the earth, beholding the evil and the good, and that diſcerneth the thoughts and intents of the heart; 'tis the word that's nigh in mouth and in the heart, which is quick and powerful, ſharper than any two-edged ſword, piereing even to the dividing aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Soul and Spirit, and of the joynts and marrow: this is the candle of the Lord that ſearcheth <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and gives light to the ſides of the earth, and corners of the world, from whom the ſhadow of death cannot hide, nor the Rocks and Mountains cover or defend; <hi>for be that formeth the Mountains, and createth the winds, and declareth or ſheweth unto man what is his thought, that maketh the morning darkneſs, and treadeth upon the high places of the earth, the Lord, the God of Hoſts is his name.</hi> This is the Spirit of truth that convinceth the world of ſin, and that ſets mens ſins in order before them, and reproves and ſmites in ſecret for evil, and that brings to judgment the hidden things of <hi>Eſau;</hi> from this eye or light of the Lord thou canſt not hide thy ſelf no more than <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Cain</hi> could, though thou ſhouldeſt hate the light
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100326:13"/>(which ſheweth thee thy thoughts) and love the darkneſs ſo as to dwell in it,
<note place="margin">No hiding from the eye of God.</note> yet the light or eye of God will purſue thee and find thee out; Hell nor the utmoſt parts of the earth, and darkneſs cannot ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure thee from the
<note n="*" place="margin">Mans condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is juſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hates the light, the way and means of Salvation.</note> juſt condemnation of God; becauſe thou hateſt the ſhining of his light, and ſtopeſt thy ear againſt the voice and teaching of it, and loveſt the darkneſs, and dwelloſt in it, while thou doeſt ſo, thou chooſeſt the way of death, and neglecteſt the means of ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that God hath ordained: for this is the <hi>condemnation of the world, that light is come into it, and men love darkneſs rather, becauſe their deeds are evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as the firſt ſtep towards reſtoration and everlaſting happineſs, thou art required
<note n="†" place="margin">The firſt ſtep in the way to life, or towards ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting happineſs.</note> to turn thy mind from the darkneſs in which thou dwelleſt, to the light Eye or Spirit of God, and to decline the power of Satan that works in the darkneſs, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the power of God; and when thou doſt but begin to do ſo, thou wilt find the ſcales to fall from thy eyes by degrees, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100326:14"/>the veil to be taken off thy heart, and the ſetters and chains of darkneſs to be looſed, and the priſon doors opened; ſo when thy candle is lighted, and thy eye opened, thou wilt diſcern thy way out, and ſee the Angel of the Lord go before thee, and guide thee in the ſame: And thou wilt alſo perceive what is in thy houſe, and clearly underſtand what hath lodged in the dark room of thy heart, and when thou comeſt to ſee things as they are,
<note n="†" place="margin">Miſtake in the underſtanding con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the nature of things that do preſent themſelves before mankind, is the cauſe of error. Thence it is that ſome call darkneſs light, and light darkneſs.</note> thou wilt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive wiſdom, to give them names according to their nature, and to judge righteouſly concerning them: and as thou loveſt this light, thou wilt be enabled by it to divide betwixt thought and thought, and begin to make conſcience of a thought, and to hate every vain thought; and when thou canſt not be eaſily rid of them, nor remove them from their old lodging-place, thou wilt breath and cry to the Lord in the Spirit, as one of old did, who was burthened and oppreſſed with their company: <hi>Search me and try me, O God, and know my heart, try me and know my thougts, and ſee if there be any wicked way in me, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100326:14"/>lead me in the way everlaſting.</hi> This is the cry which the Lord hears, and will anſwer in due and needful time. And <hi>Jeremiah</hi>'s cry to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was, <hi>Waſh thy heart from wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs, that thou mayeſt be ſaved, how long ſhall thy vain thoughts lodge within thee?</hi> Now the only way to diſlodge them, and to be rid of their company,
<note place="margin">The way to be rid of evil thoughts and to ſee their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</note> is to ſhew them no coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, make no proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for them, give them no entertainment, but by the light of God which diſcovers them to be thy enemies, judge them, and keep thy mind exerciſed in the light and power of God, that it is turned to; and not in thy thoughts, and imaginations, give them no regard: and though they do and may ariſe, purſue and compaſs thee about like Bees, yet thou keeping thy eye fixed in the light and power of God, which is as nigh thee as thy thoughts are, and ſheweth them unto thee, thou wilt ſee them in due time ſcattered as chaff before a fierce wind, and deſtroyed as ſtubble before a devouring fire.</p>
            <p>Now as thou comeſt to be a believer in the light, and to truſt in the power of God, to which thy mind is turned, thou wilt become in very deed a child of it, and ſoon be able to ſay, darkneſs is paſt, and the true light now
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100326:15"/>ſhineth, by which thou canſt ſee and judge every thought and motion that ariſeth and ſtirreth in thy mind, whether evil or inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, hurtful or harmleſs, and have wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to order them accordingly. And this is that primitive wiſdom mankind had in the beginning, but he abode not in it, through looking at the temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and beauty of the thing preſented to the eye of his mind,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>A dam</hi>'s tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was inward and myſterious.</note> or through receiving from the Woman (for he was not deceived with the beauty of an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or ſome other outward fruit, nor by the talk and perſwaſion of any creature; like our Engliſh Snakes, or the Devil in the ſhape of it, as vain man in his carnal mind ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines when he reads the Hiſtory thereof: but the temptation was more myſterious and inward) the Woman was deceived in her Thoughts; in her Judgment and Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding was ſhe beguiled before ſhe obeyed the Tempter, it appeared <hi>good for food,
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.6.</note> pleaſant and deſirable,</hi> and able to make one wiſe, before ſhe eat,
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.14. Rom. 8.20.</note> or gave to her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man being deceived, was in the trangreſſion ſubjected to vanity; not
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100326:15"/>willingly, but through <hi>hope;</hi> ſhe hoped to find the Serpents words true, and to become more wiſe, and more happy, by taking the Serpents counſel; but inſtead thereof, fell into the depth of miſery: the ſame danger attends the Children of light, the Sons and Daughters of God, (for <hi>Adam</hi> was a Son of God before Tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on)
<note n="*" place="margin">The Sons and Children of God, of the light, and of the day are only capable to fall as <hi>Adam</hi> did; and not the children of the Devil &amp; Darkneſs; they are to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored into Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, into upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, before they are in danger to fall from it as <hi>Adam</hi> did.</note> And it is only ſuch who are in the reſtorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, children of the light, and of the day, that are capable to fall as <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> did, and to ſin after the ſimilitude of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Tranſgreſſion, and to loſe innocency, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, holineſs and upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as they did, (and be driven out of the Garden of God, as they were.) Such as were never in it, nor ever dwelt in the ſtate of reſtoration, innocency, purity and holineſs, cannot be ſaid to fall from, or loſe it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Children of Darkneſs, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Devil, who have gone aſtray from that womb, and always dwelt in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, end in the region and ſhadow of death, never knew what a harmleſs innocent eſtate is, what the life of purity and holineſs is,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100326:16"/>nor what the ſimplicity of the Goſpel and Chriſt is, ſo cannot be beguiled as the Serpent did <hi>Eve,</hi> of that they never knew, nor had as men and women now in the world) yet such are beguiled by the Serpent in another sort; not of what they have had, and did once enjoy, but of what they might have and ſhould enjoy: And this he effects by keeping the eyes and minds of people abroad, and by perſwading them to follow any thing,
<note place="margin">The way and work of the Devil to keep man in the fall, in the degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, in death and darkneſs, ſlaves in his kingdom.</note> and walk in any way, rather than to turn the eye of their minds inward to the <hi>Light, Word, Power,</hi> and <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> which <hi>ſhines,</hi> which <hi>ſpeaks,</hi> which <hi>works in man,</hi> in order to <hi>lead,</hi> to <hi>teach,</hi> to <hi>guide</hi> and <hi>direct</hi> him into the way of life, and ſalvation, and to bring him into the glorious liberty of the Sons of God, into a perfect tranſlation from darkneſs to light, and from the Kingdom and power of Satan, to the Kingdom and power of the Son of God, and to know Chriſt made unto him Wiſdom, Sanctification, and Redemption.</p>
            <p>This is the bleſſed end of God in ſending his Son a light into the world,
<note place="margin">The precious love of God in ſending his Son.</note> even to enlighten the Gentile, Jew, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100326:16"/>and Prophane; and that through him they might believe and receive eternal life, and enter into that bleſſed reſt that God hath prepared, which the Primitive Chriſtians who believed, entred into; where they did not ſpeak their own words, nor think their own thoughts, nor do their own works, <hi>their heavenly Father ſpake in them, and their thoughts were thoughts of God, and he wrought all their works in them and for them.</hi> This is a bleſſed ſtate indeed, and none are entred into the reſt which God hath prepared, but ſuch as are come to witneſs and experience theſe things now in this age, as the Primitive Chriſtians did in ages paſt.</p>
            <p>For while any are found thinking their own thoughts, ſpeaking their own words, and doing their own works (though under a profeſſion of Chriſt and Chriſtianity) they cannot enter into the reſt which God hath prepared, though they may create to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves falſe reſts, and kindle a fire, and walk by the light of their own ſparks, but in the end lie down in ſorrow.</p>
            <p>True reſt and peace is obtained, or comes through a true ſelf-denial: a dying to ſelf-ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and ſelf-righteouſneſs, ſelf-thinking, and ſelf-working, contriving and inventing, ſelf-wiſdom, knowledge, and underſtanding alſo: all theſe things muſt bedenied, annihilated or
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100326:17"/>brought to nothing, and confounded: the feeding upon theſe things occaſioned,
<note place="margin">The ſeeding of the forbidden Fruit which was good in it ſelf, though not for food, occaſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and occaſioneth at this day all the miſery that attend monkind.</note> and occaſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Curſe, add all the labour and turmoil, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, forrow, and torment that hath attended, and doth attend mankind ſince the fall; to the death muſt they all come before a ſitting down in the Ringdom of God can be witneſſed, or before any can ceaſe from their own works, as God did from his.</p>
            <p>Now thou who art a child of light, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand this one thing for thy comfort and encouragement in thy warfare againſt evil thoughts; that notwithſtanding multitude of thoughts do ariſe in thee, and troops thereof attend thee, which are in themſelves ſinful; yet if thou joyn not with them in thy mind, will, and underſtanding, they are not thy thoughts, neither ſhall the evil there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of be imputed unto thee, if thou loveſt the light, and keepeſt thy mind joyned to the Spirit of God, or appearance of Chriſt in thee, that diſcovereth all temptations unto thee, in the very thought, and firſt appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of them; then thou art helping the Lord againſt the mighty; being joyned unto him, art become one with him in thy mind,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100326:17"/>and ſpirit (though in thy members there is a <hi>law,</hi> a <hi>power</hi> that wars againſt thee) and as thou abideſt with the Lord, waiting upon him, even as the <hi>eye of a Maid waits upon the hand of her Miſtreſs;</hi> he will ſave and deliver thee and ſubdue all thy enemies, even thoſe of thy own houſe, which are the greateſt enemies.</p>
            <p>Though temptations may, and will attend thee, yet it is no ſin to be tempted,
<note place="margin">It is no ſin to be tempted.</note> though with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward temptations; neither art thou to account thy ſelf, nor to be accounted a ſinner, becauſe ſin and vain thoughts may preſent themſelves in thee, in thy warfare eſtate, yet thou mayeſt ſay as <hi>Paul</hi> did, <hi>It is no more I, but ſin that dwelleth in me; and that in me, that is in my ſteſh dwells no good thing:</hi> which fleſh thou art now in the way to know withers as the graſs,
<note place="margin">Fleſh, and ſin that dwells in it, may be deſtroved, and the earthen veſſel cleanſed, and the creature deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, even on this ſide the grave.</note> and the glory of it become as the ſaded flower of the field, and ſin that dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth therein deſtroyed, and the creature of Gods making preſerved, the earthen veſſel that holds the heavenly treaſure ſanctified and ſaved, and delivered from the yoak of bondage
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100326:18"/>the whole Creation of God groans under. And this thou ſhalt certainly arrive at, as thou keepeſt thy eye upon thy <hi>Saviour,</hi> thy <hi>light,</hi> thy <hi>way,</hi> thy <hi>Captain,</hi> whom thou wilt ſee go before thee conquering, and to conquer, till all his and thy enemies are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued, brought under, and deſtroyed, and thou made as a King, as a Prieſt to God,
<note n="*" place="margin">Leſt thou ſhouldſt ſtumble at thoſe ſayings, conſider that <hi>John</hi> was the greateſt Prophet that was born of a woman, yet the leaſt in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom was greater than he.</note> meeker than <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſtronger than <hi>Sampſon,</hi> wiſer than <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> and more patient than <hi>Job;</hi> as thy elder brother was, and as the Primitive Chriſtians were, who could ſay, <hi>as he is, ſo are we in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent world, pure as he is pure, holy as he is holy, righteous as he is righteous,</hi> harmleſs and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent as he was, and in all reſigned up unto the will of God: not my will (ſaid the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Adam</hi>) but <hi>thine,</hi> though his will was as innocent and harmleſs as the firſt <hi>Adams</hi> was before the fall, and did excel: when thou comeſt up hither, thou wilt underſtand and receive what I ſay, till then it will be as a myſtery and hard ſaying to thee.</p>
            <p>And in thy way take heed of thinking, willing, and running, that obtains not the prize, ſtand ſtill and ſee the ſalvation of God;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:100326:18"/>mind above all, the arm of his power in thee, which is able to ſuppreſs thy thoughts, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie thy will, ſtop thy running, and give thee perfect ſtrength to reſiſt the Devil, and make him flee, and to furniſh thee to every good word and work, and give thee dominion over thy own ſpirit, whoſe property is to be <hi>ſwift in thoughts, eager in deſire, and reſtleſs in the accompliſhment thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now it is written, he that hath rule over his <hi>own ſpirit is ſtronger than he that rules a City;
<note place="margin">Conſider the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and in the light try and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare thy ſelf there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and thou wilt find the truth thereof.</note> and he that hath no rule over his own ſpirit is like a City broken down, and without walls: when the righteous bears rule, the land rejoyceth; but when the wicked, the land mourneth.</hi> Theſe things are infallibly true, while the uſurper keeps the throne, the Prince of Peace and his peaceable government is not known. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation and anguiſh comes upon every ſoul of man that doth evil,
<note place="margin">No opinion nor profeſſion of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where evil thoughts and evil doings ſtands, avails any thing.</note> that thinketh and imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth evil, and that yields his members ſervants to unrighteouſneſs, let his opinion, profeſſion, and talk of Religion be what
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:100326:19"/>it will, <hi>he that commits ſin is of the Devil:</hi> and without returning from it, a finiſhing or ending of it, and righteouſneſs ſet up in the room thereof, will (with the Devil) have the wages and reward of the ſame, and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs the fruit of their own thoughts and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</p>
            <p>Now it is a heavenly eſtate to live under the government of Chriſt, to know and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience him, ſwaying the Scepter in the heart, and eſtabliſhed in the throne thereof: but this none comes to enjoy, till they have firſt known him to ſit as a Refiner, with fire; and as a Fuller with ſoap; and as a Spirit of judgment and burning; and as the ſtronger man to diſpoſſeſs the ſtrong man, ſpoil all his goods, ſweep and cleanſe the houſe, and to furniſh it again with heavenly goods, with heavenly thoughts, with heavenly deſires and meditations, and all things elſe that becomes the houſe of the Lord: Holineſs to the Lord was written or engraven upon the Crown and Plate of Gold, and all the furniture of the outward Temple was ſanctified, of which this is the anti-tipe, or ſubſtance; as he that enjoys it well knows.</p>
            <p>And now it is the duty of a Chriſtian to watch in the light againſt evil thoughts, and to uſe the axe of God, which is laid to the root of them, that their ſpringing again may
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:100326:19"/>be hindered, and the end of them prevented; ſo alſo it is the duty of every one, when good thoughts, and deſires, ſprings in the room thereof to cheriſh them, to joyn with them, and to keep their eye unto the Lord that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat them, or raiſed them up in the heart: and ſo they may be called Gods thoughts, being of his own bringing forth, of his own begetting; being thoughts of purity, thoughts of peace and righteouſneſs, thoughts of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and joy in the inward man, which thoughts thou of thy ſelf cannot think;
<note place="margin">Good thoughts are of Gods own be getting, and very comfortable to a Chriſtian, and are the fruit and effect of keeping and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying the Law of God within the heart, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.14, 15</note> theſe are comfortable thoughts, juſtifying and excuſing thoughts, thoughts that will ſtand approved in the light, and the end and tendency of them is good, even as pleaſant fruit to the ſoul; ſo that ſuch can ſay as <hi>David</hi> once did, <hi>How precious are thy thoughts unto me, O Grd, how great is the ſum of them? if I ſhould count them they are more in number than the ſand; when I awake I am ſtill with thee.</hi> As thot loveſt the light, and delighteſt in the Law of God, and meditates therein, theſe good thoughts will multiply, and increaſe in thee, to thy great content and ſatisfaction: But the thoughts of the wicked
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100326:20"/>are ſin, and ſin brings trouble,
<note place="margin">Proverbs 15.26.</note> anguiſh and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; men are accuſed or excuſed in their thoughts. It is ſaid <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhazzer</hi> was ſo much troubled with his thoughts, <hi>that his countenance was changed, and the joynts of his loins were looſed, and his knees ſmote together,</hi> Dan. 5.6. Many are the amazing, ſcaring, tormenting thoughts that attends the wicked, <hi>whoſe feet run to do evil, and make haſte to ſhed innocent blood; their thoughts are thoughts of iuiquity, waſting and deſtruction are in their paths; the way of peace they know not, and there is no judgment in their goings,</hi> &amp;c. Iſa. 59.7, 8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now the thoughts of the righteous are right, and thoſe that commit their way to the Lord, their thoughts ſhall he eſtabliſhed:</hi> And that's a bleſſed ſtate indeed, to have good thoughts eſtabliſhed in the heart, in the mind,
<note place="margin">The effect of good thoughts when e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed in the heart.</note> ſuch can go forth, and come in, in peace, lie down and riſe up in peace, live and walk in peace, and praiſe the God of peace, who is bleſſed for evermore: And this is the peace, the inward peace, which the world with all its treaſures and pleaſures cannot give, nor by its frowns take away, and is the portion of all that get victory over their own
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:100326:20"/>thoughts, imaginations, luſts, defires and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections; and that do alſo keep in the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and power of God, that when good thoughts are eſtabliſhed in them, and are ſo made partakers of the Divine Nature, that they naturally think good thoughts, thoughts of love, peace, and obedience, (as they did while in the degeneration think the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) yet in this ſtate of innocency and harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſs to be diligent in the wiſdom of God, to dreſs and keep the Garden,
<note n="*" place="margin">Many may eat and drink unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily, deck them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with Gold Jewels, and play the harlot with them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> leſt thou ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving found honey, eat more than may ſuffice to nouriſh the right birth, leſt thou feed thy ſeed thy ſelf without fear, eat and drink and riſe up to play, grow idle and wanton, through plenty, and ſo forget the Lord, and let his benefits ſlip out of thy mind, and ſlight his Commandments, and let pride and exaltation in thy ſelfiſh ſpirit grow up again, as the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> and others did, mentioned in the holy Scriptures, which are written for our <hi>learning and admonition, upon whom the ends of the world are come,</hi> 1 Cor. 10, 11. therefore <hi>let him that thinketh he ſtands, take heed leſt he fall.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:100326:21"/>
               <head>Concerning the Life, State, and Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a True Chriſtian.</head>
               <p>THE life of a Chriſtian, of an Iſraelite indeed, in whom is no guile, is a life of innocency, peace, and content; quietneſs and true ſatisfaction abounds in the inward man, he is always doing well, ſo none can harm him; he always lives in the fear of God, which taught him to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from iniquity,
<note place="margin">He that lives in the love, fear, and favor of God, needs not fear men nor Devils.</note> and now preſerveth him out of the ſame, he loveth God and his Neighbour, and hates no man, ſo fears not what man can do unto him; his bread is ſure, and his water fails not, ſo he takes no thought for to morrow, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives every day his daily bread from the Lord; he liveth without care, neither doth he toil nor ſpin; the Lillies life he knows, which <hi>Solomon</hi> in all his wiſdom and glory wanted, or was not arrayed with: if he hath Wife or Children, Houſe or Land, or the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Corn, Wine and Oyl, he looks upon them as things below, ſo doth not ſet his heart and affection upon them; he looks
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:100326:21"/>upon them as they are, and loves them in their places, but not more than Chriſt: he loves the Lord above all, he loves to keep his Conſcience void of offence towards God, and towards man above all; and if he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not enjoy his Eſtate and Relations according to the will of God, he is ready, and willing to part with them, and can ſay as <hi>Job</hi> did, <hi>The Lord giveth, and the Lord taketh away; bleſsed be the name of the Lord.</hi> He is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of evil tydings, the ruffling of the winds, and the roaring of the Sea, doth not amaze nor affright him, he lives the life of Faith, which gives him victory, and enables him to overcome all things,
<note n="*" place="margin">The true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſtands always armed; though not with carnal wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons.</note> he keeps on the helmet of it, and the breaſt-plate of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the ſword of the Spirit, ſo is always armed againſt all aſſaults of the world, fleſh, and the Devil; and he knows the name of the Lord as a ſtrong tower, as a ſhield, as a buckler, as a wall of defence, and is prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſuffer and endure all things, like a good Souldier with a ſettled countenance, and holy reſolution: And though by men he may be accounted ſmitten and forſaken of God, and not fit to live upon the earth, yet he enjoys heavenly conſolation, pure tranquility of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:100326:22"/>mind, refreſhment, comfort, and joy in the inward mon; the Kings Daughter is all glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious within, and all things that do, or can befal a Chriſtian on this ſide the Grave,
<note place="margin">The preſent en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God, is more eſteemed, more valued by the true Chriſtian, than all things viſible.</note> are not worthy to be compared to the glory that <hi>is and ſhall be revealed in him:</hi> And if there was no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward on the other ſide the grave, he would not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change his life and condition, for all the glory, riches, and excellency the world can afford, ſeeing and accounting it all vanity and vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſpirit, yea. leſs than nothing, and lighter than vanity, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.17. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62.9. having found the precious pearl (which the ſwine regard not) he is willing to part with all for it, knowing the wonderful vertue, riches, and power thereof, bids adieu to all the fading treaſures, and pleaſures of <hi>Egypt;</hi> chuſing rather to ſuffer affliction and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for righteouſneſs ſake, than to enjoy the Court-pleaſures of Princes; and he is a great gainer hereby, even in this life, on this ſide the grave, a hundred fold: he finds by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience that ſaying true, <hi>Codlintſs with content is great gain, and is profitable unto all things, having the promiſe of the life that now is, and of that which is to come,</hi> 1 Tim. 4.6.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:100326:22"/>
               <p>So though the true Chriſtian ſeems (in the judgment of the wiſe in their own conceit, to loſe the enjoyment of his life, honour, riches, profit, pleaſure, preferment, relations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">No true enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of any thing, but in the will of God, and true ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denial.</note> inſtead thereof he finds them all; and in the true ſelf-denial enjoys them all, and is able to ſay as <hi>Paul</hi> did to the Corinthians, ſpeaking of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and other Chriſtians, <hi>as ſorrowful, yet al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways rejoycing; as poor, yet making many rich; as having nothing, yet poſseſſing all things;</hi> having <hi>learnt to be content in all eſtates and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<note place="margin">Content the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant companion for a Chriſtian.</note> knowing how to ſuffer want, and how to abound, every where, and in all things,</hi> &amp;c. And where there is true content, there is no want, no poverty, no ſorrow, but what is turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to plenty, riches, and rejoycing. In ſum, the true Chriſtian hath found the ſtone of the wiſe men, (or the univerſal tincture) or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine which cureth all inward diſeaſes of the ſoul, mind, and ſpirit;
<note place="margin">The wonderful ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, vertue, power, and operation of the precious pearl, none knows but he that hath it.</note> makes him ſound and clean every whit, works mighty wonders for him, makes him more precious
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:100326:23"/>than Gold, yea, than fine Gold; makes him rejoyce in ſorrow, ſing in the ſtocks, makes a Dangeon a Palace, Bonds and Chains liberty; makes Poverty Riches, turns loſs into gain, darkneſs into light before him: theſe and many more are the vertues and powerful ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of the precious Pearl, the white Stone, the elect and precious Stone, the chief corner-ſtone (which the wiſe Maſter-builders ſet at naught and ſtumble at, and will not uſe in their Building) but to the Chriſtian indeed he is precious, he is his foundation, corner, and top-ſtone alſo; and as a treaſure better than mountains of Gold, and as a Rock out of which iſſueth the water of Life, that makes the River of Pleaſure, that never ceaſeth running at the right hand of God: theſe things are known and enjoyed by the true Chriſtian, as he arrives at the mark of the high calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus, and all that are but travellers therein, taſte of the ſame in the way thereto; but the bare pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor, or formaliſt, or titular Chriſtian knows nothing hereof: for,</p>
               <p>The life, riches, and enjoyment of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is inward and hidden; his life is hid with Chriſt in God, none knoweth it but he that hath it; his converſation is with God in Heaven, and his treaſure is laid up where he walks and dwells, and where he ſits in
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:100326:23"/>heavenly places with his Saviour Chriſt Jeſus, who is made unto him wiſdom, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſanctification and redemption, and not only ſo, but he is come to ſee what is the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of the Myſtery, which from <hi>the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the world hath been hid in God:</hi> he is come to know the <hi>Lord one, and his name one,</hi> to the <hi>one Body, one Spirit, one Hope, one Faith, one Baptiſm, one Way, one Truth, one Life, one God and Father of all, who is above all, through all, and in all.</hi> This is the bleſſed <hi>end</hi> of all the appearances, manifeſtations, and diſpenſations, under all the variety of names, and various workings of the one eternal God towards mankind ever ſince the fall, menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned throughout the Holy Scriptures, and witneſſed to by the true Chriſtian, who real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enjoys the end of <hi>Paul</hi>'s bowing his knees,
<note n="*" place="margin">Not to Jeſus the Son of <hi>Abraham, David,</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> Saint, or Angel, but to God the Father, all worſhip, honour, and glory is to be given through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> or prayer unto the Father of his Lord, his Jeſus, and his Chriſt, of whom the whole Family in Heaven and Earth is named, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>Now when the true Chriſtian hath travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led through multiplicity into unity, through the various diſpenſations, operations, and workings of the Spirit of God before the Law, under the Law, through the Law, to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:100326:24"/>the Prophets, and to the miniſtration of <hi>John,</hi> and ſo to Jeſus the Son of <hi>Abraham, David,</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> and hath
<note n="*" place="margin">The only Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an; all other Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages to places, Tombs, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques are vain and fruitleſs.</note> followed him from the Manger to the Croſs, and from thence to the Grave, and know a being dead and buried with him, and a riſing with him; and not only ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe things that are above, but hath found them, having known and experienced Chriſt in all his Offices, as the great Ordinance
<note n="†" place="margin">Theſe things are not only to be read, profeſſed, and tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of, but experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally known.</note> of God, as a Mediator, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciler, Interceſſor, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of peace, healer of the wound, and maker up of the breach the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> made, as a quicken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Spirit, and Lord from Heaven; as a King, Prieſt, and Prophet; as a Saviour, San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifier, and Redeemer; as a Purifier and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker an end of ſin, and bringer in of everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Righteouſneſs; and as a High-Prieſt to preſent to God without ſpot or wrinkle, or any ſuch thing: when he is thus known to perform all theſe offices in and for his people, he is then by ſuch known to ſit down at the right hand of God, having accompliſhed the work the Father gave him to do, having put
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:100326:24"/>all things under,
<note place="margin">This is the aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Chriſt up where he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he deſcended, and before there was any cauſe for his deſcenſion: he that can underſtand let him.</note> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored all things into their primitive order, he then is alſo known to ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der up the Kingdom to the Father, and God to become all in all:
<note n="*" place="margin">Thus the Lord is known one, and his name one.</note> here the firſt is known to be laſt, and the laſt firſt; the beginning the end, and the end the beginning; and the heavenly reſt with him who is without beginning or end: I ſay reſt with him, in a pure coeleſtial ſtill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, from all ſelf-working, willing, running, and thinking; and though an innocency, or innocent ſelf be attained unto, and a harmleſs will known, yet that muſt not act, work, will, run and think of it ſelf, as the true Chriſtian (who hath travelled and experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, as before is hinted) knows right well; being always of his elder brothers mind and frame of ſpirit, ſaying to his Father, <hi>Not my will, but thine:</hi> Herein he receives wiſdom to dreſs and keep the Garden, power and ſtrength to reſiſt and overcome the Serpent in Paradice, and the Dragon in Heaven, and to keep his habitation in the heavenly City <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> which comes down from God out of Heaven, whoſe walls are ſalvation, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:100326:25"/>whoſe gates are praiſe for ever and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Worſhip of a Chriſtian, or the Christian Worſhip) what it ſtands in, and how it is performed.</head>
               <p>THere is a great conteſt in Chriſtendom among the diverſe Sects and bare pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions of Chriſtianity about Worſhip; and many are the Modes, Manners, Forms and Ceremonies that are cried up among them; every Sect conceiving, imagining and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing his Way, Manner, and Faſhion to be right, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all being full of Diſpute, Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and quarrelling one with and againſt another, envying and hating one another, fighting, killing, and deſtroying one another about them, when they are all but of their own deviſing, forms and images of their own making; moſtly from the example of Jews, Gentiles, and Apoſtate Chriſtians; and are not led thereto, nor guided therein by the unerring Spirit of God; as their fruits make fully manifeſt to the great ſcandal of the Chriſtian Religion.</p>
               <p>Now the true Chriſtians Worſhip is in the Spirit, and in the Truth, not in the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:100326:25"/>nor in the Form, barely, but was before all Letters, and outward Laws and Preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions were, before all inventions were, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all errors, and the ſpirit of them was: This was the Worſhip in Paradice; when mankind neglected this worſhip he fell into evil, into invention, into error,
<note place="margin">Sin was the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion (or cauſe) of the Law, the labour of the Prophets, and the coming and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering of Chriſt.</note> which was the cauſe of the outward Law, and all other diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations of God, for the recovery of loſt man: And before he can wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs a return out of his loſt eſtate, he muſt come again to the ſame Worſhip in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and in the Truth (even the Truth in the inward parts) (for that is it which God loves) to the word in the mouth, to the law in the heart, and the fear in the inward parts, from all fear towards God, taught by the precepts of men, from all traditions of men of corrupt minds, from all devices and inventions of men: This is the bleſſed eſtate the true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is come into, and is the end, ſum, and ſubſtance of all holy Writings, Forms, and holy Traditions, Miniſtrations, and Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations before the Law, under the Law, and the Prophets, Wilderneſs <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and Temple-Worſhip which ſtood in divers bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exerciſes, outward works and ſervices,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:100326:26"/>variety of Offerings, obſerving of Times, Days, Months, and Years, Meats, Drinks, outward Waſhings and Purifications, New Moons, Faſts, Feaſts, ſolemn Meetings, and general Aſſemblies once a Year at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> all theſe things were but ſhadows and typi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal; And this is the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titipe and
<note n="†" place="margin">The ſubſtance of all ſhadowy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices under the Law.</note> ſubſtance ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed forth by them all. To come to the Worſhip in the <hi>Spirit,</hi> in the <hi>Truth,</hi> to <hi>Mount Sion,</hi> the City of the living God, the heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and to <hi>come to the general Aſſembly and Church of the firſt-born, written in Heaven, and to God the Judge of all, and the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect,</hi> &amp;c. and to know the heavenly City that comes down from God out of Heaven, even <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> the Mother of all the living Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens thereof, whoſe Law and Covenant is ſpiritual, and writ in their hearts; whoſe love, fear, and obedience to God, is engraven in their inward parts: and from hence ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the true Worſhip in the Spirit, and in the Truth.</p>
               <p>And this is the Worſhip the Primitive Chriſtians came to, and were exerciſed in, they prayed in the Spirit, not at any ſet time, or appointed place only, but at all times, and in all places, according to the Exhortations,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:100326:26"/>
                  <hi>pray always, pray continually,</hi> pray without ceaſing, <hi>I will that men pray every where, lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up holy hands without wrath or doubting,</hi> always breathing to the Lord in Spirit, though never a word be uttered; in the clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, when the door is ſhut, the Lord heareth, and anſwereth this Prayer: and many times they were, and are alſo led forth to pray in words publickly, but moſtly for the ſake of others, and in the behalf of others, as Chriſt Jeſus did.</p>
               <p>The true Chriſtian is alſo a preacher of Righteouſneſs, not only in Words, Sentences, and long Sermons, at ſet times, and appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted places, but in life and converſation;
<note n="†" place="margin">A true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an is always preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> in this he is always a Preacher, a Teacher of that which is good, always as a candle burning, and ſet in the right place; his lamp trimmed, and his light ſhining, always as a City upon a hill, as the ſalt of the earth, and light of the world, to ſeaſon and give light to others, by holy example, which preacheth lowder than words.</p>
               <p>The true Chriſtians ſinging or rejoycing is alſo in the Spirit, and in the Truth, (and not in iniquity) and with a good underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; he needs no art not invention to bring words into Meeter or Rhime, that they
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:100326:27"/>may make a pleaſant ſound, and a joyful noiſe;
<note place="margin">The Chriſtian Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick is not made by Art and Air.</note> his Muſick doth not ſtand in outward ſounds, made by Art and Air, but his melody is in his heart, in the ſpirit, in the inward man, in the hidden man of the heart, which is the antitipe and ſubſtance of all outward muſick uſed in the time of the Law, under the firſt Covenant, in the Worſhip and Service of God; and as far exceeds it, as the ſubſtance of a thing doth the ſhadow thereof: And he that hath this heavenly inward rejoycing, and pleaſant melody in the heart, will never invent to himſelf inſtruments of Muſick (like <hi>David</hi>) nor delight in the ſounds thereof. Where this heart-melody is loſt, the outward invented muſick is ſet up, among Jews, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, and Apoſtate Chriſtians; for the true Chriſtian is come to know Chriſt Jeſus, as a Prince of Peace, as a peaceable Saviour, as the Conſolation of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and joy of genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; as a giver of peace, which the world cannot give nor take away, which far ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſeth all the delights of the ſons of men, which by nature, art, and invention they can attain unto.</p>
               <p>Now the Spirit of God is univerſal, and the Truth is univerſal, and the true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Worſhip that ſtands in it, is alſo (to be)
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:100326:27"/>univerſal; that is, at all times, and in all places; not only when people meet together in a ſolemn manner to wait together upon God, and to he or his word preach, and be preached, and to hear a Prayer, Pſalm, Song, or Hymn, even from his own pure motion and Spirit, one hour in ſeven,
<note place="margin">The true Worſhip of God ſtands not in any outward ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of time, or place, or any bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily exerciſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; but in doing the will of God, bowing in his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and obeying the voice thereof.</note> or one day in ſeven (which is good and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable in its place) but every hour, and every day, bowing in ſpirit, worſhiping in the Truth, which makes free from all error, from all evil, from all vain obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, literal traditions, and humane inventions about the Worſhip of God, from all carnal Ordinances, as <hi>Muſicks, Meats, Drinks, Waſhings, Feaſts, Faſts, Days, and Times,</hi> which ends, vaniſheth, or periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with the uſing (though holy and ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant in their firſt inſtitution) theſe things are not to be touched, nor taſted, no nor ſo much as handled by the true Chriſtian; theſe things are but beggerly elements, and world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rudiments which had a beginning, and muſt have an end.</p>
               <p>And the root or cauſe of a Chriſtian, which is Chriſt, is the end of the Law, and all the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:100326:28"/>types and ſhadows of it, and fulfils all the righteouſneſs of it, of the Prophets, and of <hi>John</hi> alſo, and is a bringer in of a better hope, a better Law, a better Covenant, a better Worſhip; which Hope, Law, Covenant and Worſhip is inward, and ſpiritual, and not outward, and carnal, formal nor traditional; and all that are come to this worſhip in the Spirit, and in the Truth, which is one pure eternal principle of light, life, and power, and have their hearts tendred by it, and their minds exerciſed in it, their thoughts and meditations guided by it, they
<note n="*" place="margin">Let the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty try themſelves hereby.</note> are come to the myſtery of the fellowſhip of the Goſpel, to the bleſſed unity wherein is no ſtrife, no wrangling, diſputing, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention; no treachery, wars, cruelty, or vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; becauſe they are all minding one thing, learning of one teacher, following of one guide, <hi>viz.</hi> the Grace and Spirit of God: and though they have diverſity of gifts, and are attained to different degrees of Faith,
<note place="margin">Different ſtates and growths in the Truth, no cauſe of diſ unity.</note> of Grace, of Knowledge, Growth and Salvation in the ſame, and are ſome as a foot, ſome as a hand, eye, ear, and mouth, yet are all as members of one body; and the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:100326:28"/>meaneſt hath unity with the more noble, the greateſt with the leaſt, the loweſt with the higheſt, the ſtrongeſt with the weakeſt; nor is there any Jar or Schiſm in this well framed Body, of which <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction,</hi> the <hi>Annointing</hi> is the Head and Teacher, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This heavenly unity is the antitype of the Seamleſs-Coat of Chriſt, wove from top to bottom (which the Souldiers did not rend, tear, or divide, but caſt lots for) and of that Law that forbade weaving linnen and wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len together, and ſowing mingled ſeed.</p>
               <p>Now there is no unity, no agreement, no concord betwixt light and darkneſs, ſin and righteouſneſs, (Chriſt, and <hi>Belial</hi>) theſe things of a different and contrary nature cannot unite, cannot agree, though they are nigh to each other, ſowen in one field. God hath ſowen a good ſeed in the field of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, the enemy hath ſown an evil ſeed, and in many it hath taken root, and ſprang up above the good ſeed,
<note place="margin">Before there can be true unity in and among mankind, the ſeed of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent muſt be brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and rooted out of the heart.</note> even among thoſe profeſſing Chriſtianity it ſelf; and from hence ariſeth and groweth all the evil will, envy, hatred, ſtrife, cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, violence, blood-ſhed, wars, and murthers, in whole Chriſtendom, and till the head of this evil ſeed be not only
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:100326:29"/>bruiſed, by the promiſed ſeed which God hath ſowed, but rooted out alſo of the heart of man, all theſe things will grow up; theſe evil effects can never ceaſe till the cauſe be removed, and taken away, as the true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian knoweth right well by experience.</p>
               <p>Now the Chriſtians indeed, as they live and abide in this pure external principle of Light, Life, Spirit, and Truth, they have unity one with another, and fellowſhip with God; they are the brethren whoſe living to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in unity is comely to behold, who have the one mind, one heart, one ſoul, and have their minds, hearts, and ſouls always governed, ruled, and ordered by the good Spirit of God: as every one lives and keeps this order, ank undor this heavenly govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they cannot chuſe but live together in unity, in love, in good will, in peace, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly concord, and agreement, every one within himſelf, with God, and with each other, and in love to all mankind: here is the end of ſtrife, wars, and fightings come unto,
<note place="margin">The end of Wars, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> (both within, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out) and this is the time and ſtate wherein inſtruments of War and Cruelty, are turned into inſtruments of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary uſe; and as they abide herein, they can learn war no more, according to the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:100326:29"/>bleſſed ſight and Propheſie of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> that Evangelical Prophet. Here <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is known a quiet habitotion, the inhabitants thereof being eſtabliſhed in peace and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, far from oppreſſion (the cauſe of War and Oppreſſion being taken away, which is evil thicking, evil ſpeaking, and evil doing; and this every one muſt know and experience before they can be eſtabliſhed in peace, before they can know the peace of God which paſſeth all underſtanding, to keep their hearts and minds, and to rule in their hearts, and to know the aboundings of it, and to delight therein; as it is
<note n="*" place="margin">The enjoyment of thoſe things men do, and may wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, are on this ſide the Grave.</note> written, <hi>the meek ſhall inherit the earth, and delight them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the abundance of peace;</hi> the earth, nor earthly things ſhall not inherit them; they tread upon the high places of it, and reign like. Kings and Princes over all the glory thereof. Oh!
<note place="margin">Read the 25th. and 35th. Chapter of <hi>Iſaiah</hi>'s Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and wait in the precious Faith thou haſt received, till thou enjoy the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling thereof.</note> this is a bleſſed ſtate indeed, wait all to poſſeſs and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy it more and more: this is the bleſſed end of the Goſpel of petce, and of the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. My breathing is,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:100326:30"/>that all that profeſs it, may come to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit Peace, Righteouſneſs, and Joy in the inward man; even to lie down in that peace where none can make afraid, and to dwell on that holy Mountain, where no deſtroyer is; and to inhabit that City whoſe Builder and Maker is God: to whom be praiſe and glory for evermore.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>W. S.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:100326:30"/>
               <head>A few Words added to the ſenſible Reader.</head>
               <p>THou who art awakened out of the ſleep of death, and riſen out of the grave of ſin, and ſea of corruption, and art come to the exerciſe of thy ſpiritual ſenſes, ſo that thou canſt hear, ſee, taſte, and handle the things of God, thou, well knoweſt that the bleſſed end of all holy mens words and writings, teſtimonies and declarations, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from the love of God) is, that others that are yet unholy, wandering about in and after the vanity of their own minds, thoughts, and imaginations upon the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren Mountains; even as ſheep without a Shepherd, may come to be gathered and brought home to the fold of reſt, where ſafety, peace, and ſatisfaction is to be found for their weary ſouls, who have long wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in deſolate places, ſeeking reſt, but finding none; ſpending their time, labour, and money for that which doth not profit, feed, and nouriſh up unto eternal life. I ſay, to direct theſe ſtrangers, wanderers, labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and unſatisfied travellers into the way of reſt and peace, is the bleſſed end of all
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:100326:31"/>Words and holy Writings, even that ſuch may come to poſſeſs, enjoy, and inherit the things ſpoken, and written of; without which, all hearing, reading, ſeeking, enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, toiling, labouring, ſpending time and money is to no purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Now it is the mind, the ſoul, the ſpirit of man that wants reſt, that is gone from its center, that hath loſt it ſtay, habitation, and dwelling-place in God; and innumerable are the thoughts, imaginations, devices and inventions, willings and runnings, that poor mankind in this eſtate is exerciſed in, and carried away with both Jew and Gentile, Profeſſor and Prophane upon the face of the whole earth: For in all Sects and ſorts of Religions, thoſe who are ſincere and devout therein, propoſe this end to themſelves in the exerciſe thereof, <hi>viz.</hi> to attain a ſtate of happineſs and felicity at laſt: Many are the ways, means, and precepts, preſcriptions, directions, and obſervations, that men give and receive from one the other, enjoyn and perſwade one the other; and ſometimes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel one another by violence, to walk in, and make uſe of, in order to arrive thereto, as they think and imagine; but it is in this age: as of old, the guides and teachers of the people cauſe them to err, cauſe them to go aſtray, and wander from the right way
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:100326:31"/>of the Lord, they were in viſion, judgment, and underſtanding themſelves, and cauſe all that follow and obey them to do the ſame, being unskilful guides, and blind watchmen, are but as the blind leading the blind, and ſo both fall into the ditch together.</p>
               <p>Now the way to everlaſting happineſs is but one, both to Jew and Gentile; which way is Chriſt, who is the wiſdom and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God, the Truth, and the Life; and the appearance of this Chriſt, of God, is within men, in their hearts: its firſt appearance is as a light ſhining in darkneſs, and as a pure ſpotleſs Spirit, that conſenteth to no evil, but reproveth and convinceth all that are found in it; and to this Light or Spirit, all who write or ſpeak for God, and the good of mankind, do turn and direct the minds of men, and endeavour to perſwade them to give regard unto its reproofs of inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as being the way to life, and to obey its counſel and teaching, as the only means of ſalvation, and way of returning to the rock from whence they were hewen, and to the hole of the pit from whence they were dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, to their habitation, and dwelling-place in God again; and many thouſands in this Iſland and other places, can give teſtimony that this is the only way and means God hath ordained for the recovery, return, and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:100326:32"/>reſtoration of loſt man; and that all other ways and means which they had been weary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves in, availed nothing; but walking in this heavenly way, the Light, the Spirit, and Grace of God within, and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the annointing within, they come to witneſs ſalvation came to their houſe, and to ſurround them as walls and bulwarks, and to witneſs the fulfilling of that Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, <hi>My people ſhall dwell in a peaceable habitation, and in ſure dwellings,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 30.3, 4.32.18.</note> and in quiet reſting-places. The eye of them that ſee ſhall not be dim, the ear of them that hear ſhall bearken, the heart alſo of the raſh ſhall underſtand knowledge, and the tongue of the ſtammerer ſhall be ready to ſpeak plainly.</hi> Theſe are the bleſſed effects of walking in the way and paths of righteouſneſs, which a remnant are living witneſſes of, and can praiſe and magnifie the name of the Lord in the ſenſe thereof.</p>
               <p>But none comes to enjoy this bleſſed eſtate, nor inhabit this heavenly dwelling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place, but as their minds comes truly to be exerciſed by and in the Light of the Lord, and that by walking and abiding therein, come to have their minds eſtabliſhed, ſettled, and ſtayed upon him, who is indeed the alone ſtay of his people, and rock of his inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:100326:32"/>
               <p>And nothing can be found in the heavens above, nor in the earth beneath, that is able to ſatisfie or ſtay the mind of man, but the Lord, the mind or ſoul of man is more no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, more excellent than all viſible things, ſo they are not all capable to fill or ſatisfie his ſoul, or ſtay his mind, though he might poſſeſs or have the whole world to himſelf, yet in the end will be made to cry out and confeſs, with the Preacher of old, <hi>Vanity of vanity, all is vanity and vexation of ſpirit,</hi> &amp;c. Eccleſ. 1. But to have the mind ſtayed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lord, there is pleaſure, peace, and content, truly found and enjoyed, according to the teſtimony of that Divine Prophet <hi>Iſaiab,</hi> who ſaid, ſpeaking in the name of the Lord, <hi>Thou wilt keep him in perfect peace whoſe mind is ſtaid upon thee.</hi> This is ſuch a truth, that none knoweth but he that hath it; it may be ſoon writ, read, or ſpoken, but to enjoy that eſtate is more than words, it is the end, ſum, and ſubſtance of all that can be ſaid or done, and is the reward of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous from the immediate hand of God, <hi>viz. to be kept in perfect peace:</hi> It's the end of all holy breathings and deſires, its the end of the Preaching the Goſpel of Peace and Sal-Salvation, even to know, and feel, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience the peace of God, to keep the heart, and to keep the mind, and to rule there.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:100326:33"/>
               <p>This is a bleſſed ſtate indeed, worthy to be waited for, and preſſed after, by all that have a ſight, and ſence thereof, and are in the way that leadeth thereto though not yet arrived thereat; go forward in the name of the Lord, even in that name <hi>Light,</hi> by which he hath made himſelf known unto us in this age, by which Light thou ſaweſt the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering, and unſtableneſs of thy mind, and the multitude of thy thoughts, imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and inventions; perſevere in the ſame and thou wilt become not only a child of it, but alſo grow from a Childs eſtate, to the ſtate of a young Man, Elder, and Father; keeping the Faith, and firmly believing, that which ſheweth thee the wandering and unſtableneſs of thy mind, will be as a Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds Crook unto thee, and in due time will bring thee back into the fold of reſt: and, that that holy Light that diſcovers, and ſheweth unto thee thy thoughts, and inward enemies, will alſo by the brightneſs of its ariſing, diſperſe and deſtroy them for thee, and bring thee into that eſtate thy ſoul de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrieth, panteth, and looketh after, even in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the preſence of the Lord, where the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Joy is, and where the rivers of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures run; where the reaping and return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with joy is, where the ſinging for joy of heart is, and the joy of Gods ſalvation felt,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:100326:33"/>the bleſſed Light of God, or Son of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, in whom thou haſt belleved, is the only way to poſſeſs and inherit thoſe things. And thy walking, ablding, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevering in it, is the means, and there is not any other way or means appointed of God, to bring man back into that Paradiſical ſtate of felicity he loſt by Tranſgreſſion, and to the eſtabliſhing him in it.</p>
               <p>But all that walk not, nor ablde and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere therein, after they are come into it, never attain to that bleſſed end of its appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſhining to them; for a bare know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Truth, and a profeſſion of the Light and Spirit of God within, if they walk not in it, and are not guided and lead by it, it avails nothing, but rather draws down fierce wrath and vengeance upon the head of ſuch, who know their Maſters will and do it not, who talk and profeſs well, but are found doing evil, and thereby lay a ſtumbling-block in the way of the blind, and cauſe the way of Truth to be evil ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, and the Name of the Lord (by which he hath made himſelf known in this Age) to be blaſphemed, by reaſon of their unged<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deeds, under a Profeſſion of Godlineſs, and Cloak of Righteouſneſs, ſuch their dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation ſlumbreth not.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:100326:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>And this I teſtifie and declare to all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to whom this may come (which may ſerve alſo as a caution and warning to them) that if they meet with any under the Name, Form, and Profeſſion of a Chriſtian (in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt called a Quaker) who in his Converſe, Trade, and Dealing, Commerce, and Affairs doth not let his <hi>Yea,</hi> be <hi>Yea,</hi> and his <hi>Nay, Nay,</hi> but breaketh his word and promiſes, there is need to have a ſpecial care of that man, and look upon him as one falſe and deceitful to the holy Principle of Truth, and as a Hypocrite under the Profeſſion of it; He that is falſe to God; cannot be true to men: thou hadſt better truſt and give credit to a Heathen or Infidel, than to ſuch a one. No wickedneſs beyond that which is acted under a peculiar Cloak of Religion. Such who gain Credit and Repute by wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Cloak, and get Widows and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phans Monies into their hands, to create great Trades by Sea and Land, and then break, are ſome of the worſer ſort of Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and Cheats, and the cry of the poor Fatherleſs and Widows cries lowd againſt them. This is a ſhort Teſtimony ariſing in my heart againſt this ſort of Wickedneſs, wherein I have a little eaſed my mind, and in the Truth remain a Friend to all men.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>W. S.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
